Register of the Milton Genecin papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Milton Genecin papers
1906-1987
89016
Genecin, Milton, 1908-1989
48 manuscript boxes (20 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, minutes, internal bulletins, other internal party documents, serial issues, and pamphlets, relating to socialist and communist movements in the United States, especially the Socialist Workers Party, and to activities of Trotskyist groups abroad.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1908 Born in Russia
1913 Immigrated to United States
1935 Joined Socialist Party
1938 Founding member, Socialist Workers Party
1940 Founding member, Workers Party, following split in Socialist Workers Party
1941 Left Workers Party and returned to Socialist Workers Party
1957-1971 National Committee member, Socialist Workers Party
1983 Expelled from Socialist Workers Party. Founding member, Socialist Action
1989 Died, Los Angeles, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Milton Genecin reflect his long membership in the Socialist Workers Party from its founding convention in 1938 up until 1983, when he was one of a number of veteran members who left or were expelled from the party. Genecin was sequentially active in the New York City, Akron, Toledo and Los Angeles branches of the Socialist Workers Party. He was the party organizer for some time in each of the last three cities, and was for a number of years a member of the National Committee of the party. In party work he used the pseudonym Milton Alvin. The papers provide detailed documentation of the interior life of the party during the decades of Genecin's membership. They are divided into five series.
The Correspondence series consists overwhelmingly of Genecin's correspondence with other party members. It retains the chronological arrangement initiated by Genecin himself. While this may not be optimal for some purposes, it is ideal for others, bringing together as it does letters to and from multiple individuals discussing contemporaneous party situations.
The series of Speeches and Writings by Genecin is also arranged chronologically. It includes both lectures and articles written for public outlets, on the one hand, and internal party speeches and discussion papers, on the other.
The series of Internal Documents consists of assorted items circulated internally within the Socialist Workers Party. These include minutes, resolutions, theses, discussion papers, and mimeographed or photocopied transcripts of letters and other documents. Some notes by Genecin on party meetings are also included. This series too is arranged chronologically.
The series of Internal Bulletins is very substantial. It consists of items susceptible to treatment as serials but intended for internal use only within the Socialist Workers Party. They are arranged by title and thereunder numerically/chronologically. Bulletins issued by youth or other affiliates of the party are included.
The series of Printed Matter consists mainly of pamphlets intended for public consumption. Most of these were publications of the Socialist Workers Party or related organizations or presses. There is a separate subseries of pamphlets issued by unrelated organizations or presses, and other small subseries for serial issues and clippings.
The Milton Genecin Papers were acquired by the Hoover Institution from Thelma Genecin in 1989, soon after her husband's death.
The abbreviation SWP is used for the Socialist Workers Party in various places throughout the register.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Socialist Workers Party.; Fourth International.; Socialism--United States.; Communism--United States.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1940-1983; 1-4 (Box 1-4:)
  Includes enclosures. Correspondents include Jack Barnes, Natalie Bombaro, George Breitman, Joel Britton, Pierre Broué, Bob Burkart, Peter Camejo, James P. Cannon, Steve Clark, George Clarke, Bert Cochran, Oscar Coover, Farrell Dobbs, Ross Dowson, Vincent Dunne, Tony Dutrow, Ernest Erber, Les Evans, Dianne Feeley, Fred Feldman, Dave Frankel, Sam Gordon, Joseph and Reba Hansen, Asher Harer, Gus Horowitz, Cindy Jaquith, Doug Jenness, Linda Jenness, Tom and Karolyn Kerry, Gabriel Kolko, Mark Lause, Rich Lesnik, Frank Lovell, Caroline Lund, Staughton Lynd, Don MacDonald, Paul Montauk, George Novack, Art and Ethel Preis, Evelyn Reed, Harry Ring, Dick Roberts, Annette Rubinstein, Marvel Scholl, Bev Scott, Larry Seigle, Ted and Dot Selander, Max Shachtman, Tom Shachtman, Art Sharon, Ed Shaw, Barry Sheppard, Jean Simon, Louis Sinclair, Morris Stein, Alan Wald, Mary-Alice Waters, Stan Weir, Dave Weiss, Murry and Myra Tanner Weiss, George and Connie Weissman, B. J. Widick, and Milton Zaslow
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1940 (Folder 1: 1)
  - 1941 (Folder 1: 2)
  - 1947 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1948 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1949 (Folder 1: 5)
  - 1950 (Folder 1: 6)
  - 1951 (Folder 1: 7)
  - 1952 (Folder 1: 8)
  - 1953 (Folder 1: 9)
  - 1954 (Folder 1: 10)
  - 1955 (Folder 1: 11)
  - 1956 (Folder 1: 12)
  - 1957 (Folder 1: 13)
  - 1958 (Folder 1: 14)
  - 1959 (Folder 1: 15)
  - 1960 (Folder 1: 16)
  - 1961 (Folder 1: 17)
  - 1962 (Folder 1: 18)
  - 1963 (Folder 1: 19)
  - 1964 (Folder 1: 20)
  - 1965 (Folder 1: 21)
  - 1966 (Folder 2: 1)
  - 1967 (Folder 2: 2)
  - 1968 (Folder 2: 3)
  - 1969 (Folder 2: 4)
  - 1970 (Folder 2: 5)
  - 1971 (Folder 2: 6)
  - 1972 (Folder 2: 7)
  - 1973 (Folder 2: 8)
  - 1974 (Folder 2: 9)
  - 1975 (Folder 3: 1)
  - 1976 (Folder 3: 2)
  - 1977 (Folder 3: 3)
  - 1978 (Folder 3: 4)
  - 1979 (Folder 3: 5)
  - 1980 (Folder 3: 6)
  - 1981 (Folder 4: 1)
  - 1982 (Folder 4: 1)
  - 1982 (Folder 4: 2)
  - 1983 (Folder 4: 3)
- Speeches and Writings, 1940-1985; 4-11 (Box 4-11: 3)
  Speeches and writings by Milton Genecin, arranged chronologically
  - "On Shachtman's Answer to the Position of the S.W.P. on Conscription, War and Militarism,", circa 1940 November (Folder 4: 4)
    Workers Party internal document. Typescript
  - "Is the Soviet Bureaucracy a New Class?", circa 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 5)
    Workers Party internal document. Holograph and typescript
  - Speeches and notes from Workers Party internal meetings re Russian question and trade union question, circa 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 6)
    Holographs and typescripts. Includes some Workers Party internal documents
  - "Resolution on Proletarian Military Policy,", 1941 February 12 (Folder 4: 7)
  - "The Proletarian Revolution and the Defense of the Soviet Union,", 1941 August 1 (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Bolshevism and the Workers Party,", 1941 September 17 (Folder 5: 1)
  - "A Statement to the Convention" (with Milton Zaslow and others), circa 1941 September-October (Folder 5: 2)
    Statement leaving Workers Party and returning to Socialist Workers Party. Typescript
  - Speech, SWP national convention, 1941 October (Folder 5: 3)
    Typescript
  - Report on SWP national convention at internal SWP New York City meeting, 1942 (Folder 5: 4)
    Holograph
  - Notes on Japan, 1944 (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Impending Visit of G. L. K. Smith Makes Akron Workers Angry," Militant, 1946 (Folder 5: 6)
    Printed copy
  - "Akron Rubber Unions Vote Strike for Wage Increases," Militant, 1946 (Folder 5: 7)
  - "Rubber Workers,", 1947 March 23 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Article re Harold J. Laski, circa 1949 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Speeches at internal SWP Toledo, Ohio meetings, 1950 (Folder 5: 10)
    Holograph and typescript
  - Speeches and reports at internal SWP Los Angeles meetings, 1952 (Folder 5: 11)
    Holographs and typescripts
  - "Soviet Russia and Stalinism,", 1953 May-June (Folder 5: 12)
    Public lecture series. Typescripts
  - Leon Trotsky memorial meeting speech, 1953 August (Folder 5: 13)
    Typescript and mimeograph
  - Speeches, reports and notes at internal SWP Los Angeles meetings, 1953 (Folder 5: 14)
  - "Coexistence or World Revolution?", 1954 August (Folder 5: 15)
    Leon Trotsky memorial meeting speech, Los Angeles. Typescript
  - Report on Trotsky School at internal SWP meeting, 1954 (Folder 5: 16)
  - "Can America Have Another Recession?", 1955 (Folder 5: 17)
  - "Soviet-American Relations Today,", 1956 April 6 (Folder 5: 18)
    Speech. Typescript
  - "Labor and the Democratic Party,", 1956 October (Folder 5: 19)
    Public speech, Los Angeles. Typescript
  - "Murder in Dixie,", 1956 (Folder 5: 20)
    Public speech. Typescript
  - Speech re 20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, 1956 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1957 (Folder 5: 22)
    Holograph and typescripts
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1958 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Speech re political situation in France, 1958 (Folder 5: 24)
    Public meeting. Typescript
  - Khrushchev Visit and World Peace, 1959 October 2 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Article re James Reston, 1959 November (Folder 6: 2)
  - Speeches and reports at internal SWP meetings, 1959 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Socialism Challenges Capitalism for World Supremacy, 1959 (Folder 6: 4)
    Russian Revolution anniversary speech. Typescript
  - Speeches and notes at internal SWP meetings, circa 1950s (Folder 6: 5)
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1960 (Folder 6: 6)
    Holographs and typescript
  - World Peace and the New Kennedy Administration, 1961 February (Folder 6: 7)
  - "I Didn't Know about the Worms" (re Cuba), 1961 March (Folder 6: 8)
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1961 (Folder 6: 9)
  - "New Developments in Cuba,", circa 1961 (Folder 6: 10)
  - "The Role of Theory in the Transition from Capitalism to Socialism,", circa 1961 (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Analysis of Peculiarities of Russia's Development,", 1962 February 23 (Folder 6: 12)
    Lecture on Leon Trotsky, History of the Russian Revolution. Typescript
  - "The Nature of the Chinese Communist Party,", 1962 July 10 (Folder 6: 13)
  - "100 Years of Asia in Revolt,", 1962 July-August (Folder 6: 14)
    Lecture series, Los Angeles. Holographs and typescripts
  - "The Old Futzer,", 1962 December (Folder 6: 15)
  - Speech re civil liberties, circa 1962 (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Unionism and Its Critics,", circa 1962 (Folder 6: 17)
  - "The Peking-Moscow Dispute,", 1963 February 24 (Folder 6: 18)
    Report at internal SWP meeting, Los Angeles. Typescript
  - "The Hilde MacLeod School of Quotation,", 1963 April (Folder 6: 19)
  - "The Moscow-Peking Dispute,", 1963 May 1 (Folder 6: 20)
  - "On Trotsky's Writings, 1929 to 1936,", 1963 August 11 (Folder 6: 21)
  - Speeches and reports re China, John F. Kennedy assassination, and other matters at internal SWP meetings, Los Angeles, 1963 (Folder 7: 1)
  - "Union Problems in Southern California,", circa 1963 (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Khrushchev Downfall,", 1964 (Folder 7: 3)
    Speech at public meeting. Typescript
  - "Workers and Technology,", 1964 (Folder 7: 4)
    Holograph and typed notes
  - "To the Memory of Art Preis,", 1965 January 15 (Folder 7: 5)
    Memorial meeting speech. Typescript
  - Article re Vietnam, 1965 August 9 (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Speech, Yetta Fine memorial meeting,", 1965 September 29 (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Is World War III Inevitable?", 1965 (Folder 7: 8)
    Typescripts
  - Review of Alexander Werth, Russia at War, 1941-1945, 1965 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Speech in debate with Ben Dobbs of Communist Party, Los Angeles, 1966 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1966 (Folder 7: 11)
  - "The Soviet Union, China and Vietnam,", 1966 (Folder 7: 12)
    Lecture at SWP camp. Typescript
  - "Notes on Current Tasks and Opportunities,", 1967 February 11 (Folder 7: 13)
    SWP internal document. Typescript
  - Speech at Steve Roberts memorial meeting, 1967 September 10 (Folder 7: 14)
  - "Crisis in Higher Education in California,", 1967 (Folder 7: 15)
  - "Fiftieth Anniversary of the Russian Revolution,", 1967 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Report on political situation in France, internal SWP meeting, Los Angeles, 1968 July 2 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Speech at Hy Struman memorial meeting, 1968 August 11 (Folder 7: 18)
  - Speech at public Leon Trotsky memorial meeting, 1968 September (Folder 7: 19)
  - Speech re youth, internal SWP meeting, 1969 February (Folder 7: 20)
  - "May Day,", 1969 May 1 (Folder 7: 21)
    Banquet speech. Typescript
  - "Fiftieth Anniversary of the Communist Party," International Socialist Review, 1969 July-August (Folder 7: 22)
    Review of George Charney, A Long Journey. Printed copy
  - Speech at Emily Thornton memorial meeting, 1969 December 9 (Folder 7: 23)
  - Speeches and reports at internal SWP meetings, circa 1960s (Folder 7: 24)
  - "Readings for Revolutionaries," Militant, 1969-1970 (Folder 7: 25)
    Newspaper column on recommended books. Typescripts
  - "Military Policy and Draft,", 1970 November (Folder 7: 26)
  - Introduction to new edition of Leon Trotsky, The Revolution Betrayed, 1970 (Folder 7: 27)
  - "May Day,", 1971 May 1 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Review of new edition of Leon Trotsky, The Third International after Lenin, Militant, 1971 June 25 (Folder 8: 2)
  - "History of American Trotskyism, 1919-1939,", 1971 June 25-26 (Folder 8: 3)
    Internal SWP lecture series, Berkeley. Typescripts
  - "Concept of the Leninist Party,", 1971 June-July (Folder 8: 4)
    Internal SWP lecture, Los Angeles and San Diego. Typescript
  - Speech in internal SWP debate on the document "For a Proletarian Orientation,", 1971 July 11 (Folder 8: 5)
  - "Labor Radical a Dishonest History of the CIO," International Socialist Review, 1971 July-August (Folder 8: 6)
    Review of Len De Caux, "Labor Radical. Typescript and printed copy
  - "Political Aspects of the Economic Crisis,", 1971 September 26 (Folder 8: 7)
  - "A Distorted Story of Labor," Militant, 1971 November 19 (Folder 8: 8)
    Review of Richard O. Boyer and Herbert M. Morais, Labor's Untold Story. Typescript
  - "The Stalin-Hitler Pact,", 1971 December 14 (Folder 8: 9)
    Internal SWP lecture. Typescript
  - "The Economic Crisis and the Wage Freeze," Militant, 1971 December 17 (Folder 8: 10)
  - "Theses on American History,", 1971 (Folder 8: 11)
  - "25th Anniversary of the Theses on the American Revolution,", 1971 (Folder 8: 12)
  - "The Economic Crisis and the Unions,", 1972 January 5 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Review of Writings of Leon Trotsky, 1934-35, Militant, 1972 January 21 (Folder 8: 14)
  - "The Aerospace Wage Decision: A Warning,", 1972 January 24 (Folder 8: 15)
  - "College Man Graduates to Garbage Truck,", 1972 February 3 (Folder 8: 16)
  - "Profits Up, Wages Down, Unemployment Remains,", 1972 February 6 (Folder 8: 17)
  - "Union Bureaucrats," Militant, 1972 February 11 (Folder 8: 18)
  - "Was Stalin's Pact with Hitler Justified?" International Socialist Review, 1972 February (Folder 8: 19)
  - "Shock Treatments for the Workers," Militant, 1972 March 24 (Folder 8: 20)
  - "A Bull Market in Beef," Militant, 1972 April 14 (Folder 8: 21)
  - Review of new edition of Leon Trotsky, "The Stalin School of Falsification, Militant, 1972 April 14 (Folder 8: 22)
  - Review of George Morris, Rebellion in the Unions, Militant, 1972 May 5 (Folder 8: 23)
  - "What the Democratic Primaries Have Revealed,", 1972 May 24 (Folder 8: 24)
  - "Communist Party Policy in the 1972 Elections," Militant, 1972 June 23 (Folder 8: 25)
  - Review of Richard J. Walton, Cold War and Counterrevolution, Militant, 1972 June 30 (Folder 8: 26)
  - Review of Writings of Leon Trotsky, 1933-34, Militant, 1972 July 21 (Folder 9: 1)
  - Review of Art Preis, Labor's Giant Step, Militant, 1972 August 11 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Review of Joyce and Gabriel Kolko, The Limits of Power, Militant, 1972 September 22 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Review of Leon Trotsky Speaks, Militant, 1972 November 17 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Obituary of Max Shachtman, Militant, 1972 December 1 (Folder 9: 5)
  - "The American Revolution in Its Historical Context,", 1972 December 16 (Folder 9: 6)
    Internal SWP lecture, Oakland. Typescript
  - "California Tax Burden Shifted from Rich to Poor," Militant, 1972 December 29 (Folder 9: 7)
  - "Teamsters President Scabs on Farm Workers," Militant, 1972 December 29 (Folder 9: 8)
  - "Dr. Starsky's Dilemma,", 1972 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Reports at internal SWP meetings, 1972 (Folder 9: 10)
  - "The United States in the Second World War,", 1972 (Folder 9: 11)
  - "Farm Union Wins Legal Victory," Militant, 1973 January 19 (Folder 9: 12)
  - "Harry S. Truman, from Average American to President" (re death of Truman), Militant, 1973 January 19 (Folder 9: 13)
  - "Stalinist Ghoul at Work" (re Communist Party commentary on Max Shachtman), Militant, 1973 March 2 (Folder 9: 14)
  - "The Shoe Is On the Other Foot,", 1973 March 26 (Folder 9: 15)
  - "Democratic Centralism and the International," SWP Discussion Bulletin, 1973 April (Folder 9: 16)
  - "New Light on J. Edgar Hoover,", 1973 May 15 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Review of John Lewis Gaddis, The United States and the Origins of the Cold War, 1941-1947, Militant, 1973 June 15 (Folder 9: 18)
  - Review of Louis Nizer, The Implosion Conspiracy, and Walter and Miriam Schneir, Invitation to an Inquest, Militant, 1973 June 29 (Folder 9: 19)
  - "Fortieth Anniversary of Hitler's Rise to Power,", 1973 June (Folder 9: 20)
  - "It Is Time to Call a Halt!" SWP Discussion Bulletin, 1973 June (Folder 9: 21)
  - "The Spanish Revolution,", 1973 July 7 (Folder 9: 22)
  - "California Communist Leader Resigns" (re Dorothy Healey), Militant, 1973 July 27 (Folder 9: 23)
  - "An Open Letter to Jeff Meisner," SWP Discussion Bulletin, 1973 July (Folder 9: 24)
  - "Americans Discarding Political Illusions,", 1973 August 30 (Folder 9: 25)
  - "Fifty Years of Stalinist Treachery," Intercontinental Press, 1973 September-October (Folder 10: 1)
  - "Civil Liberties Union Opposes Death Penalty," Los Angeles Weekly News, 1973 October 12-19 (Folder 10: 2)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "A Criticism of 'Draft of World Political Resolution,'", 1973 October 24 (Folder 10: 3)
    Internal SWP document. Typescript
  - "Dissent in the Soviet Union,", 1973 November (Folder 10: 4)
  - Speeches and reports at internal SWP meetings, 1973 (Folder 10: 5)
  - "Solzhenitsyn and Soviet Dissidents,", 1974 February 8 (Folder 10: 6)
    Public speech, Berkeley. Typescript
  - "Why Solzhenitsyn Was Exiled,", 1974 March (Folder 10: 7)
    Public speech, San Francisco and Los Angeles. Typescript
  - "The Struggle against Fascism in Germany,", 1974 May 4-5 (Folder 10: 8)
    Internal SWP lecture series, Seattle. Typescript
  - Lecture on Leon Trotsky, History of the Russian Revolution, 1974 June 19 (Folder 10: 9)
    Internal SWP lecture, Los Angeles. Typescript
  - Speech at James P. Cannon memorial meeting, Los Angeles, 1974 September 3 (Folder 10: 10)
  - "Bill Kitt: Revolutionist for Half a Century" (obituary), Militant, 1975 May 23 (Folder 10: 11)
  - "Tradition, Orientation and Program," SWP Discussion Bulletin, 1975 June (Folder 10: 12)
  - "Revisionism and Opportunism," SWP Discussion Bulletin, 1975 July (Folder 10: 13)
  - "Tom Kerry's Witch-Hunt," SWP Discussion Bulletin, 1975 July (Folder 10: 14)
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1975 (Folder 10: 15)
  - "Workers in the American Revolution," Butcher Workman, 1976 March-June (Folder 10: 16)
  - "The Jim Cannon That I Knew," in James P. Cannon as We Knew Him, 1976 (Folder 10: 17)
  - "The Socialist Workers Party in World War II,", 1976 (Folder 10: 18)
    Internal SWP lecture, Pasadena and Long Beach. Typed notes
  - Review of Bert Cochran, Labor and Communism, International Socialist Review, 1978 December (Folder 10: 19)
  - "On Class Nature of Kampuchea under Pol Pot,", 1979 July (Folder 10: 20)
    Speech at internal SWP meeting. Holograph and typescript
  - "Snapping To,", 1981 March 2 (Folder 11: 1)
  - "The Constitution of the Socialist Workers Party,", 1982 December 24 (Folder 11: 2)
    Typescript and notes
  - "The 1982 SWP Election Campaign," (Folder 11: 3)
  - Speeches at internal SWP meetings, 1982 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Speech at Samuel Pollock memorial meeting, California State University-Northridge, 1983 March 14 (Folder 11: 5)
  - "A Tribute to Leon Trotsky and James P. Cannon," Socialist Action, 1985 September-October (Folder 11: 6)
- Internal Documents, 1937-1983; 11-19 (Box 11-19: 6)
  Socialist Workers Party minutes, resolutions, theses, discussion papers, and circulated letters and other documents, and notes.
  Arranged chronologically
  - 1937 (Folder 11: 7)
    Socialist Appeal Institute minutes (predecessor of SWP)
  - 1938 (Folder 11: 8)
    Includes minutes of SWP founding convention
  - 1940 (Folder 11: 9)
    Includes "From 'Science' to Slander" by Joseph Hansen; "The Truth about the Auto Crisis" by George Clarke; convention documents; "Proletarian Military Policy"
  - 1942 (Folder 11: 10)
    Constitution
  - 1943 (Folder 11: 11)
    Symposium on Leon Trotsky, In Defense of Marxism
  - 1946 (Folder 11: 12)
    Includes resolutions on wages and prices and on withdrawal of occupation troops; report on Pioneer Publishers; "From a Propaganda Group to a Party of Mass Action"
  - 1947 (Folder 11: 13)
    Includes resolutions on Workers Party and on Johson-Forest Tendency; circulated correspondence with French and British sections
  - 1948. (Folder 11: 14)
    Includes membership statistics; radio address by James P. Cannon; "American Trade-Unions in the Postwar Period and SWP Tasks"; resolution on Workers Party; thesis on Negro question; report on The Militant
  - Undated, circa 1940s (Folder 11: 15)
    Includes "Draft Resolution on the Negro Question"; "The Tearse Letter" by J. Lyons
  - 1951 (Folder 11: 16)
  - 1952 (Folder 11: 17)
    Includes convention agenda; "SWP 1952 Presidential Election Platform"; Los Angeles Local minutes
  - 1954 (Folder 11: 18)
    Amended constitution
  - 1955 (Folder 12: 1-2)
    - June-August 2. (Folder 12: 1)
      Includes "Pabloism Reviewed" by Peng Shu-tse; "The Third Chinese Revolution and Its Aftermath"; "The Rise of the Colonial Bourgeoisie"
    - August 12-September (Folder 12: 2)
      Includes "The Soviet Union Today"; "Some Problems in Assessing the Chinese Revolution" by Joseph Hansen
  - 1956 (Folder 12: 3)
    Includes discussion material on Nikita Khrushchev speech at 20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and on tactical approaches to members of the Communist Party; "The World Today"; draft resolutions on Stalinism, the new regime in Hungary, and the Middle East
  - 1957 (Folder 12-13:)
    - January-May 11 (Folder 12: 4)
      Includes "International Perspectives"; reports and discussion material on regroupment; documents on British section; "Memorandum on the International Situation" by Sam Marcy; "The Class Struggle Road to Negro Equality"
    - May 14-December (Folder 13: 1)